Guide to the Milton Glass files on Kitimat Canada circa 1950-1954.
Glass, Milton files on Kitimat Canada
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Milton Glass files on Kitimat Canada circa 1950-1954.
6896
Glass
ca. 10 cubic feet
Correspondence, maps, photographs, plans, printed materials, publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Files relating to the planning and development of Kitimat, B.C..
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Architect. Milton Glass worked on the planned community of Kitimat, British Columbia. Commissioned by Alcan (Aluminum Company of Canada), it was to be British Columbia's first planned community: "Kitimat would be designed for the worker and his family. The fulfillment of people's needs as the focus of a town plan was considered revolutionary. Famed American architect and town planner Clarence S. Stein, and town planners Mayer & Whittlesey of New York fulfilled Alcan's goals. A green space model was chosen separating pedestrian and vehicular traffic and having home, store, and community building face peaceful open spaces, removed from intrusion and hazard by the automobile."
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Files relating to the planning and development of Kitimat, B.C.. The Kitimat collection goes in depth into the planning and development of all aspects of the city, starting from choosing the designers and planners of the city and ending with the evaluation of the mostly finished town. The correspondences, meeting reports, and townsite planning reports show what the planners had in mind at the time and how the town slowly evolved to satisfy the townspeople physically, mentally, and culturally. The collection also includes many photographs used to plan the landscape and various blueprints and reports which show changes between the years of planning. Various publications and attempts to publicize and advertise the town is reflected. Conflicts with the municipal and provincial government are also listed as well as attempts to resolve the conflicts. Records, receipts, correspondences, and figures show the financial struggles in planning and developing the city.
The collection includes correspondences, maps, blueprints, reports, minutes of meetings, photographs, negatives, slides, publications, contracts, receipts, material lists, graphs, advertisements, and news clippings. Notable figures (in no particular order): ALCAN (Aluminum Company of Canada Ltd.), Clarence S. Stein, Julian Whittlesey, Wilbur Smith and Associates, Edmund T. Ames, Albert Mayer, William J. Conklin, Norman Klein, J. A. Currie, Wilfrid R. Ussner, Dan Kiley, James C. Buckley, Ralph Eberlin, Walter E. Kroening, Larry Smith, Lois Barclay, N. L. Engelhardt, Larry Smith, and Roger Willcox.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Glass, Milton.; Stein, Clarence S.; Mayer & Whittlesey (New York, N.Y)
Subjects:
City planning -- British Columbia -- Kitimat.; Planned communities -- Canada.; New towns -- British Columbia -- Kitimat.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
See also the Clarence Stein papers, #3600, http://resolver.library.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/EADresolver?id=RMM03600
CONTAINER LIST
- From the Start of the Job Through to the End of W and C Participation, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  On the front of the folder, it says: "KEEP THIS FILED AT THE BEGINNING OF THE KITIMAT JOB (this involves several job numbers)"
- Townsite Report, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence Between Partners of Mayer and Whittlesey re Alcan, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence Relative to Kitimat, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- General Correspondence with Alcan, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Billing Beta - Fees, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Billing Data - Reimbursible Expenses, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Cost Estimates, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Architectural Production Costs, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Town Development Costs, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Drawings Filed in Drafting Room, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Minutes of Meetings, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Record of Plans and Reports Submitted to ALCAN, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Planning Notes, Comments, and Reports, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- James C. Buckley, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Dan Kiley - Landscape, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Telecommunications - Walter Duchinsky, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Kitimat Constructors - Correspondence with, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Sharp, Thompson, Berwick and Pratt - Architects for Alcan, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Swan, Rhodes and Wooster Report on Kitimat River Bridge, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Clarence S. Stein, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Ralph Eberlin (Utilities), 1951 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Walter E. Kroening (Community Management), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Larry Smith (Commerce and Business), 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Community Living - Planning for Reports by Lois Barclay Murphy, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Community "A" - The First Neighborhood; Home, Plot and Road: House Types and Materials, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Butler Report - Recreation, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Schools - N. L. Engelhardt, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Robert L. Davison (Howard T. Fisher Associates), 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Frederick Latzer (re Utilities), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Semmons and Simpson - Architects for Alcan, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- River Control and Mr. K. Ross, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Weather - Dr. Landsberg, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Weather Reports from Dr. Landsberg, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Maps, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Indian Mission Weather Records (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Weather - Charts, etc., 1947-1957 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Publicity, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Source Material (Empty as of August 18th 2011), No Date (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Kitimat Master Plan Report Backups of Parts I, II, II, and Index, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Part I of Report on Master Planning, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Mimeographed copy of 6.0 "Townsite Physicla Planning" as prepared by Mr. Stein's office for inclusion in the Townsite Report
- House Types and Their Relation to Land and Living; Self-Building; Landscaping, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- First Interim Report (Land Use Study and Preliminary Master Plan), 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Second Interim Report (Revised Town Plan), 1952 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Larry Smith Reports on Commercial Aspects of Kitimat and the Hotel Facility 1957, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Larry Smith Reports on Commercial Aspects of Kitimat and the Hotel Facility 1952, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Walter E. Kroening and Lawrence H. Tucker, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Report entitled "The Kitimat Project - Study of Service Personnel Requirements"; Organization - Personnel - Budget
- Stein: Progress Report for Kitimat Townsite Planning, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Howard T. Fisher Associates Report on Materials and Methods - Parts 1 and 2, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Buckley Secion of Report on Kitimat, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Aluminum Company of Canada Ltd.
- Master Plan for Service Center, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Master Plan Report for Kitimat - Part I, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Master Plan Report for Kitimat - Part II, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Master Plan Report for Kitimat - Part III, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Church Planning, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- City and Neighborhood Centers, Commercial Center, Service Center, 1952-1955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Theater Concept, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Service Center, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Parking Facilities, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Weather, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Photos
- Commercial Space - J. S. Shakespeare, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Utilities (Water, Central Heating) and Site Engineering - River Control, 1953-1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Terrace Road, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Landscaping - Dan Kiley, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Architects - Semmons and Simpson and Sharp, Thompson, Berwik and Pratt, 1952-1958 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- James C. Buckley, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Utilities - Ralph Eberlin, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Clarence S. Stein and Roger Willcox - Correspondence, 1952-1956 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Correspondence with ALCAN, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Correspondence with ALCAN, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Correspondence with ALCAN, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Town Building Documents and Correspondents, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Town Building Letters, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence With Vancouver Office, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence With Vancouver Office, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence With Corporation of the District of Kitimat Officials, 1954-1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Kitimat Community Council (Stan Rough, Chairman), 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Contract Proposal, 1952-1956 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Billing, 1952-1956 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Progress Reports, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- By-Laws and Regulations, 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- By-Laws (Comments on, bound copies), 1953 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Master Plan Revisions, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Survey, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Field Directions to ALCAN, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Maps in Connection With Field Directions, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Minutes of Meetings and Office Memos, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Architectural Production Costs, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Planning Notes (Data extracted from Report by Dudley), 1956 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Conference: Understanding the Community, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Meeting Report Back Ups, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Fall (1955) Conference: Development Program; Agendas; Proceedings, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Material for Possible Publication on Kitimat, 1952-1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Correspondence with FORUM (Haskell) re Publication, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Letters Sent to Individuals and Firms with Brochure Reprint of FORUM Article, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Publication of Mt. and Reports on Loan, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence Relative to Kitimat, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Customs Forms and Instructions on Their Use When Shipping Blueprints, 1952-1959 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Preliminary Report on Kitimat City Center - Mayer Whittlesey and Glass, July 12, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Annual Report with Info on Alcan and Other Subsidaries of Aluminum Limited, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- City Center - Draft for Final Report (Mayer Whttlesey and Glass), 1957 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- City Center Commercial Development - Volume 1 Draft, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Ripley and Associates (Soil), 1957 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Proposal, Contract, Billing, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Larry Smith and Company, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Municipality of Kitimat Federal Government, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Correspondence with Alcan re City Center, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Notes: Made by J.W. in the Field in April-May, 1957, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Eric West - re Exhibit (1955) and Later Correspondence, 1955-1958 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Publications, 1952-1954 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Architectural Forum (October 1954), Fortune (August 1952, July 1954)
- Kitimat Proposal by Mayer and Whittlesey, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Proposal Dated July 31/51, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Publications, 1953-1958 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Clarence S. Stein, Kitimat: Progress Report on the ALCAN Project
- Publicity, etc., 1950s (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Publicity and Historical and Other Data from Kitimat Newspapers and Elsewhere, 1950s (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Progress on Physical Development on Kitimat, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  Newspapers
- Publicity, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Publicity Material1954-1957, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Zoning (Draft), 1953 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Zoning, November 1956 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Zoning, 1954-1964 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Photostats of 4 Drawings, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Kitimat, 1951-1957 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Photos, material lists, correspondence, plan reviews, project plans, landscape maps, cost analyses, planning maps, charts and figures, facility plans, reports
- Kitimat Photos, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Kitimat Photos, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Kitimat Photos, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Kitimat Photos, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Kitimat Photos, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Kitimat Photos, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Kitimat Photos, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Photographs of Kitimat, Kemano, and Nechako, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Kitimat Exhibition Panels, No Date (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Reports and Small Plans from Kitimat, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Reports and Other Material Sent Direct from Kitimat to JW in Athens, 1958-1960 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Correspondence with Mariel Ames (includes Social Study of Kitimat), 1959-1965 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Consultation with the Municipality Report: Parks and Recreation (Community Plan Report), 1962 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Community Center Plans, 1959-1965 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Report: Park and Recreation, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Reports (brought back by JW Nov. 1965), 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Kitimat Negatives, No Date (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Drawing List as of January 1964, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Townsite Development Maps, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- House Plans, No Date (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Kitimat Consultancy, 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Record of Materials Sent to Julian Whittlesey in Athens, June 1960, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Henry Strub (Aluminum Secretariat Ltd., in Montreal), 1959-1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence re Kitimat, Including Correspondence with Some Alcan People, 1959-1961 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Correspondence with Mrs. Meldrm (Editor, Northern Sentinel) and Planning Articles Therein by Edmund T. Ames, 1959-1961 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Industrial Development Report (Delta Area) by Hopkins, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Edmund T. Ames (Personal), 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Kitimat Consultancy - Kitimat Townsite Report, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Bibliography (Jan. 1962): Community Plan Report Index, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Background Info - Clippings, Reports, Minutes, etc., 1961 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- CONSULTATION WITH THE MUNICIPALITY (Box 8, Folder 11-22)
  - Correspondence Reports and Bill re May/63 Trip, 1952-1963 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Traffic Survey Material Related to Wilber Smith File, 1956-1962 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Traffic survey, various sketches and maps showing intersections, correspondence
  - Wilbur Smith and Associates (Traffic), 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Contract and Billing, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with Ames and Currie, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with Ames and Currie, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Portions of Minutes of Council Meetings, 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence with W. R. Ussner (Architect), 1960 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Proposal, Contract, Billing, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Planning Personnel, 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence (Ames and Currie), 1960 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Correspondence (Ames and Currie), 1959 (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Mayer and Whittlesey Photos, No Date (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Folders of oversized items. These items are mostly plan drawings for the Kitimat area. Includes plans for the Service Center of the Aluminum company of Canada and the Kitimat Townsite Report, 1960 (Map-case W-5, Folder 1-5)
  Oversized portfolio, 2 copies; placed in the library vault, separate from the rest of the collection